Konvitz, Milton R. Papers /4039
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series I: Correspondence
  - Haifa, University of, 1973-1978 (Box 14, Folder 15)
    Correspondence with Doctor Abraham Kaplan, Provost of the University of Haifa. Konvitz agrees to serve as a member of the Academic Advisory Board of the Academy for Jewish Studies Without Walls, sponsored by the American Jewish Committee and the University of Haifa (June 1, 1973).
  - Hallane, 1968 (Box 14, Folder 16)
    Detailed letter from Martha Applegarth Hallane relative to Konvitz's review of a book by Matthew Josephson (January 26, 1968).
  - Halpern, Benjamin, 1946-1954 (Box 14, Folder 17)
    1946-1947, 1949, 1951, 1953-1954. Personal correspondence with Benjamin Halpern, director of the Department of Culture and Education of the Jewish Agency for Palestine and former Managing Editor of Jewish Frontier
  - Hampton Institute, 1966-1967 (Box 14, Folder 18)
    Correspondence with Thomas M. Law, Director of the Division of Business of the Hampton Institute, regarding Konvitz's evaluation of his visit to Hampton on March 13-14, 1967; and routine documents about the Cornell-Hampton Cooperative Program.
  - Harvard Law Review, 1947-1976 (Box 14, Folder 19)
    1947-1948 1957-1958, 1960, 1976. Correspondence with book review editors and the president of the Harvard Law Review in relation to book reviews by Konvitz and the possibility of Konvitz writing an article.
  - Hatchett Affair. (Box 14, Folder 20)
    Materials regarding John F. Hatchett. Documents concerning Hatchett and concerning his relationship to Cornell. ACCESS RESTRICTED. No date.
  - Hebrew University, 1950-1980 (Box 14, Folder 21)
    1950-1952, 1955, 1957-1959, 1962, 1965-1967, 1969-1970, 1972- 1973, 1978-1980. Correspondence with Zvi H. Bar-Niv, President of the National Labor Court, relative to the establishment of the Institute of Labor and Social Security Studies at Hebrew University. Correspondence with Professor Jacob Katz, Rector of Hebrew University, about their mutual interest in Jewish rights in the Diaspora.
  - Hayim Greenberg Teachers Seminary, 1972 (Box 14, Folder 22)
    Correspondence with Doctor Gershon Winer, Hayim Greenberg Teachers Seminary, regarding the reorganization of the Seminary. Konvitz agrees to serve as Chairman of the Academic Council of the Hayim Greenberg Institute (February 29, 1972)
  - Hayman, Eugene, 1946-1953 (Box 14, Folder 23)
    1946, 1948-1949, 1951-1953. Personal correspondence with Eugene Hayman, a former Cornell student.
  - Hebraic Studies Fund, 1959-1960 (Box 14, Folder 24)
    Correspondence and memorandums relating to the Hebraic Studies Fund at Cornell University. Professor Konvitz helped to establish the Fund for contributions to be used to purchase Hebrew books by the Cornell library.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Doctor S. Blumenfield, 1961-1970 (Box 14, Folder 25)
    1961-1962, 1964-1970. Detailed correspondence primarily with Doctor Samuel M. Blumenfield, Secretary of the Hebrew Culture Foundation and Director of the Department of Education and Culture of the Jewish Agency, regarding all aspects of the affairs of the Foundation. Doctor Konvitz has been the Chairman of the Foundation since 1962
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Blumenfield, Doctor Samuel M., 1962-1963 (Box 14, Folder 26)
    [1962- ] 1962-1963. Correspondence relating to the Hebrew Culture Foundation primarily with Doctor Blumenfield.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - By Laws, Charter, 1955-1962 (Box 14, Folder 27)
    1955, 1962. A copy of the Foundation's By- Laws which were written by Konvitz.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation (Establishment of "Chair" at Cornell), 1956-1961 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Correspondence with Doctor Judah J. Shapiro, Secretary of the National Foundation regarding the Foundation's support for Jewish scholarship at Cornell.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - General Correspondence through 1969, 1954-1969 (Box 15, Folder 2)
    1954, 1962, [1965- 1969]. Detailed correspondence with Stuart M. Brown, Junior, Dean of Cornell's College of Arts and Sciences; James A. Perkins, President of Cornell; and Professors Isaac Rabinowitz and David Patterson, relative to the Hebrew Culture Foundation's grant in support of the teaching of modern Hebrew language and literature at Cornell; Patterson's position at Cornell; and the establishment of a Department of Semitic Languages and Literature.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - General Correspondence, 1968-1971 (Box 15, Folder 3)
    1970-1971, 1968-1971. Correspondence with various people but mostly with Doctor Abraham P. Gannes, Secretary of the Foundation, on all aspects of Foundation work.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - General Correspondence, 1971-1974 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    1972-1973 [1971-1973] 1974. Correspondence with Professor Jacob Neusuer, Department of Religious Studies at Brown University.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - General Correspondence, 1973-1977 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    1974-1975 [1973]-1977. Correspondence with people involved in activities of the Hebrew Culture Foundation
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Correspondence, 1978-1980 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    1978 [1978-1979] 1980. Correspondence with persons involved in activities of the Hebrew Culture Foundation. Also reports, minutes, and memorandums.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Rose L. Halprin, 1965 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    Correspondence with Rose L. Halprin, Chairperson of the Jewish Agency - American Section and former President of Hadassah, relating to the Hebrew Culture Foundation.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Institutions, 1962-1965 (Box 15, Folder 8)
    Correspondence between Konvitz and Doctor Samuel M. Blumenfield, Secretary of the Foundation, and several colleges and universities (including Columbia University, Fairleigh Dickinson University, Baltimore Hebrew College, the University of Chicago, Hofstra College, Indiana University, Kent State University, Long Island University, the New School for Social Research, New York University, the University of Pennsylvania, Rutgers University, the University of Texas, Washington University, and West Virginia University) regarding Foundation grants and the Hebrew programs of these institutions.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Milton R. Konvitz, Chairman, 1965-1966 (Box 15, Folder 9)
    Letter from Doctor Konvitz to Dean David A. Thomas, School of Business and Public Affairs at Cornell, on the possibility of a grant to the Hebrew Culture Foundation from the Merrill Trust.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - October, 1965 - Meeting, 1963-1966 (Box 15, Folder 10)
    1963 [1965] 1966. Letter from Professor Stuart M. Brown, Junior, Dean of Cornell's College of Arts and Sciences, relative to the teaching of modern Hebrew language and literature at Cornell (October 7, 1965). Correspondence with Doctor James A. Perkins, President of Cornell. Konvitz informs Perkins of the Foundation's decision to support a position in modern Hebrew language and literature (October 26, 1965).
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Levinthal, Honorable Louis E., 1962 (Box 15, Folder 11)
    [1962- ] 1962. Correspondence with Louis E. Levinthal, former Chairman of the Hebrew Culture Foundation; and other correspondence relating to routine Foundation matters
  - Hebrew culture Foundation - Minutes, Board Meetings, 1963-1980 (Box 15, Folder 12)
    Memorandums and minutes of Board of Directors meetings for each year between 1963 and 1979 and correspondence on the activities and finances of the Foundation.
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Board Meetings 1978, 1976-1979 (Box 15, Folder 13)
    1976-1979. Includes minutes of Board of Directors meetings, financial information, and copies of the report, "The Hebrew Culture Foundation 1955-1978," by Abraham P. Gannes (November 1977)
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Neuman, Doctor Emanuel, Tarbut Foundation, Incorporated, 1962-1963 (Box 15, Folder 14)
    [1962- ] 1962-1963. Correspondence with Doctor Emanuel Neuman, President of the Tarbuth Foundation, Incorporated
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Shapiro, Doctor Judah J., 1962-1965 (Box 15, Folder 15)
    [1962- ] 1962-1965. Correspondence with Judah J. Shapiro, Secretary of the National Foundation for Jewish Culture. In a letter from Shapiro, written on the behalf of Doctor Nahum Goldmann of the World Zionist Movement, Shapiro informs Konvitz that Goldmann wants Konvitz to serve on a United States and Canada committee and to attend the committee meetings in Geneva between August 23 and August 26, 1965, at the expense of the World Zionist Organization (May 14, 1965).
  - Hebrew culture Foundation - Miscellaneous printed materials, 1962-1965 (Box 15, Folder 16)
    Includes report of programs in Hebrew and Jewish studies
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Financial Report, 1980-1981 (Box 15, Folder 17)
  - Hebrew Culture Foundation - Miscellaneous, 1966-1979 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    1966, 1968-1971, 1973-1979. Includes financial statements of the Foundation, a copy of the Foundation's certificate of incorporate, and other Foundation correspondence and material
  - Hebrew Union College - Jewish Institution of Religion, 1966-1978 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    1966-1968, 1971-1972, 1977-1978. Correspondence with administrators. Konvitz was awarded the honorary degree of Doctor of Humane Letters at the Hebrew Union College - Jewish Institute of Religion, America's Seminary of Reform Judaism, on June 5, 1966.
  - Hebrew University - Collection of Funds, 1961-1962 (Box 16, Folder 3)
  - Heller, Bernard, 1946-1977 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    Correspondence with Rabbi Bernard Heller, President of Yeshiva Rabbi Joseph Konvitz, and director of the Jewish Cultural Property Division, under the American Military Government. Konvitz comments on the "home rule" proposal by Judge Hofstadter (January 19, 1951). Other correspondence relating to the Yeshiva Rabbi Joseph Konvitz and personal matters. Also a copy of the "Certificate of Incorporate of the Bernard Heller Foundation, Incorporated."
  - Heller, Bernard, 1946-1977 (Box 16, Folder 5)
  - Herberg, Will, 1946-1956 (Box 16, Folder 6)
    Detailed correspondence with Professor Will Herberg, Drew University, on issues relating to Jewish ethics and history, theology, and Israel. Also detailed correspondence about lectures, articles, and personal matters.
  - Herberg, Will, 1957-1972 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    1957-1964, 1968, 1972. Konvitz asked Herberg to consider coming to Cornell for the academic year 1959-1960 as a visiting professor, and lecturing in Professor Konvitz's American Ideals course while Konvitz is on sabbatical (January 30, 1958). Konvitz mentions that he is planning a course or seminar for the spring semester of 1960-1961 that will focus mainly on the relations between labor and religion (November 7, 1960). Other personal correspondence.
  - Hill, Herbert, 1963-1978 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    1963-1964, 1967-1968, 1974-1975, 1977-1978. Correspondence with Professor Herbert Hill, Industrial Relations Research Institute at the University of Wisconsin-Madison and former National Labor Director of the National Association for the Advancement of Colored People, relative to Konvitz's comments on Hill's manuscripts and the arrangements for visits by Hill to lecture to Konvitz's and other professors' classes in the Industrial and Labor Relations and Law Schools.
  - Hertzberg, Arthur, 1967-1979 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    1967-1976, 1978-1979. Correspondence with Rabbi Arthur Hertzberg, President of the American Jewish Congress. Konvitz agrees to participate in a dialogue on Jewishness and the creative process as part of the April 1976 Bicentennial National Biennial Convention of the American Jewish Congress. Konvitz was a member of the Governing Council of the American Jewish Congress (April 2, 1974). Konvitz nominated Hertzberg to become a member of the Cornell Board of Trustees (February 20, 1974). Copy of a letter from William E. Simon, the Secretary of the United States Treasury, to Hertzberg on Simon's position and that of the Treasury Department on the Arab Boycott and other related issues (May 3, 1975). Also correspondence between Konvitz and Hertzberg on the Journal of Jewish Social Studies; the Conference on Jewish Social Studies; the American Jewish Congress; and their articles and other publications.
  - Herzberg, Max J., 1946-1949 (Box 16, Folder 10)
    Personal correspondence with Max J. Herzberg, Principal of Weequahic High School, Newark, New Jersey, and a member of the Executive Committee of the National Council of Teachers of English, regarding routine publication matters relating to an essay on "American Legal Writings" that Doctor Konvitz wrote for a volume Herzberg was editing on American literature. Also routine personal correspondence.
  - Hillel Foundation - Book Funds, 1965 (Box 16, Folder 11)
    Letters from Rabbi Benjamin M. Kahn, National Director of the B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundations; a copy of a news release and a memorandum to Hillel Directors from Kahn, relative to a grant from Professor and Mrs. Benjamin Siegel to Cornell to found a special Book Fund for the purchase of Hebrew and Yiddish language and literature books for Hillel Libraries. The grant was made as a result of Konvitz's initiative.
  - Hillel Book Foundation, 1966-1968 (Box 16, Folder 12)
    1966, 1968. A letter to Doctor Konvitz from Rabbi Kahn and copies of correspondence between Kahn and the Siegels on the latter's contributions to the Hillel Foundation for the purchase of books.
  - Hillel National Commission, 1965-1966 (Box 16, Folder 13)
    Letters from Rabbi Kahn. Professor Konvitz accepted nomination to membership on the B'nai B'rith Hillel Commission (January 3, 1966). Also minutes of the December 8, 1965 meeting of the Executive Committee of the National Hillel Commission.
  - Hillel Commission 1972, 1969 (Box 16, Folder 14)
    Confidential memorandums from Rabbi Kahn to members of the Hillel Commission and routine materials regarding Hillel affairs and activities. Also the "B'nai B'rith Hillel Foundation's Citation of Service" certificate to Doctor Konvitz.
  - Hillel Foundation, 1969-1980 (Box 16, Folder 15)
    1969, 1974-1975, 1978-1980. Personal correspondence with Hillel Foundation officers including Doctor Alfred Jaspe, National Director
  - Hillel Foundation, 1965-1968 (Box 16, Folder 16)
    [1966] 1965-1968. Correspondence with Hillel Foundation officers on Hillel matters
  - Hillman, Herman, 1946-1954 (Box 16, Folder 17)
    1946-1951, 1954. Personal correspondence with Herman D. Hillman, National Housing Agency.
  - Histadrut, 1965-1979 (Box 16, Folder 18)
    1965-1968, 1971, 1973-1977, 1979. Letter from Sarah Morris, Executive Director of the American Histadrut Culture Exchange Institute, regarding Konvitz's agreement to chair a panel discussion on "Israel: The Next Decade" on November 4, 1973 at the Annual Convention of the National Committee for Labor Israel (October 3, 1973). Also included are minutes and memorandums of the Board of Directors, the Executive Committee, and other committees reports and other related materials. Konvitz was also a member of the Institute's Board of Trustees.
  - Hollander, Louis, 1951-1965 (Box 16, Folder 19)
    1951-1953, 1955-1956, 1958, 1962, 1964-1965. Correspondence with Louis Hollander, Secretary-Treasurer of the New York State American Federation of Labor-Congress of Industrial Organizations and a Trustee of Cornell University, regarding personal matters and university affairs.
  - Holley, Marion - Personal, 1949 (Box 16, Folder 20)
    Personal correspondence with Marion G. Holley, one of Konvitz's former students
  - Hook, Sidney, 1965-1989 (Box 16, Folder 21)
    1965-1969, 1971, 1973-1975, 1977-1989. Correspondence with Professor Sidney Hook, Department of Philosophy at New York University. Konvitz and Hook discuss scholarly and social issues in detail. This correspondence includes discussions regarding secular humanism (November 9, 1980); discrimination against hiring Jewish professors by prestigious American colleges and universities (March 12, 1979); student activism on American campuses; black activism at Cornell (January 19, 1969); the trial which Bertrand Russell, Sartre, and other Europeans were planning to stage in opposition to the war in Vietnam (August 19, 1966); and Hook's detailed criticisms of chapters of Konvitz's Expanding Liberties. Also includes comments on each other's publications, papers, and addresses. Includes related materials such as reprints and personal correspondence.
  - Hook, Sidney, 1960-1964 (Box 16, Folder 22)
    [1960- ] 1960-1964. Correspondence with Hook on legal issues and publications. Konvitz and Hook discuss legal issues including expatriation cases, jurisprudence, constitutional liberties, preferred and strategic freedoms, Supreme Court justices, Congressional power to override Court rulings, and the statute of limitation on the charge of conspiring to organize a Communist party. Correspondence includes scholarly discussions of Konvitz's monograph, Aspects of Liberty (February 18, 1962) and Hook's The Paradoxes of Freedom (January 22, 1962). Also correspondence on the work and control of the New Leader magazine (January 6, 1961), and on personal matters.
  - Hook, Sidney, 1946-1959 (Box 16, Folder 23)
    Scholarly and detailed correspondence with Professor Sidney Hook relating to segregation, discrimination, and principles of civil liberties (December 10, 1957; February 29, 1948; and March 19, 1948); the "United States Bill of Rights" (November 22, 1957); and the Executive Committee of the American Committee for Cultural Freedom (April 27, 1954). Correspondence on social and scholarly topics, including the publication of Professor Horace Kallen's Festschrift; and on personal matters.
  - Hotels, 1950-1965 (Box 16, Folder 24)
    1950, 1958, 1962-1965
  - Hovde, Bryn J., 1947-1949 (Box 16, Folder 25)
    1947, 1949. Personal correspondence with Doctor Bryn J. Hovde, President of the New School for Social Research.
  - Hudson Review, 1948 (Box 16, Folder 26)
    Literary correspondence with the editors of the Hudson Review
  - Howe, Irving, 1967-1969 (Box 16, Folder 27)
    1967, 1969. Correspondence with Professor Irving Howe, City University of New York, relative to Howe's project to write a book on the development of secular Jewish life in the United States between 1880 and World War II - The Jewish Experience 1890-1950. Also correspondence from Howe regarding routine activities and work of the Jewish Labor Committee (July 22, 1969) and the Young People's Socialist League.
  - Hurwitz, Henry - Menorah Journal - Personal, 1947-1953 (Box 16, Folder 28)
    1947-1949, 1951, 1953. Correspondence with Henry Hurwitz, editor of the Menorah Journal. Includes detailed correspondence about Doctor Konvitz's reviews for the Journal. Copy of a letter from Hurwitz to the editor of Commentary in response to a critical letter to Commentary by Konvitz, commenting on Hurwitz's article, "Towards a Noble Community," in The Menorah Journal of Autumn 1948 (September 14, 1949). Also personal correspondence.
  - Hyams, Ario S., 1949 (Box 16, Folder 29)
    Letter from Rabbi Ario S. Hyams, the Jewish Community Center, Teaneck, New Jersey. Hyams responds to Konvitz's Commentary article, "A Plea for Religious Freedom in Israel" (October 1, 1949)
  - I - General Correspondence, 1961-1981 (Box 16, Folder 30)
    1961, 1963, 1966, 1968, 1971-1981. Correspondence with Edwin Young, Secretary-Treasurer of the Industrial Relations Research Association, on Konvitz's nomination for election to the Executive Board (May 23, 1955). Correspondence with G. Israel, Secretary-General of the Alliance Israelite Universelle, on the AIU's (?) history and its relations to its counterparts in Germany, England, and the United States (June 27, 1974). Personal correspondence with George S. Ives, Chairman of the National Mediation Board (December 31, 1974).
  - I, 1947-1959 (Box 16, Folder 31)
    1947-1948, 1950-1953, 1955-1959. Correspondence with J. Anthony Marcus, President of the Institute of Foreign Trades, regarding Konvitz's January 1, 1956 letter in the New York Times. Doctor Konvitz argues against governmental censorship of Union of Soviet Socialist Republics (USSR) publications. Konvitz also comments that it is possible to fight against Communism without joining a "crusade" (January 9, 1956). Correspondence with Roger N. Baldwin.
  - I, 1956-1967 (Box 16, Folder 32)
    1956, 1958, 1961, 1963, 1966-1967. Correspondence with Saul L. Sherman, Executive Secretary of the American Fund for Free Jurists (February 7, 1966). Personal correspondence with Morris Iuschewitz, Secretary-Treasurer of the New York City Congress of Industrial Organizations Council, member of the New York City Board of Education, and Trustee of the New York State University.
  - Injunctions, Study of the Use of - Senator Murray, Jack Barbash, Adams --sc, 1946-1952 (Box 17, Folder 1)
    1946-1947, [1950] 1952. Correspondence with several people including Jack Barbash, staff Director of the United States senate Subcommittee on Labor Management Relations; Martin P. Catherwood, Dean of the Industrial and Labor Relations School; Jacob Seidenberg, Industrial and Labor Relations graduate research assistant; and R.W. Fleming, Director of the Industrial Relations Center at the University of Wisconsin, about Konvitz's direction of a study of the use of the injunction in labor disputes in the New York City metropolitan area since the adoption of the Little Norris-La Guardia Act; and about aspects of the broader study, by the United States Subcommittee on Labor-Management Relations of the Senate Committee on Labor and Public Welfare, of the use of the injunction in labor disputes by state courts. The correspondence, memorandums, and reports provide detailed information about Konvitz's project and other areas of the Subcommittee's study. Also correspondence between Dean Catherwood and United States Senator James E. Murray, Chairman of the Subcommittee on Labor-Management Relations, on the participation of the Industrial and Labor Relations School in the study (April 1950). In addition to a number of reports and a bibliography on labor injunctions, there is a copy of "A proposal for a Workshop in Group Relations in Union Administration and Collective Bargaining."
  - Injunction Study - Use of the Injunction - Senator James Murray, Jack Barbash, Adams, 1950-1951 (Box 17, Folder 2)
    Correspondence with various people including Jack Barbash, Dean Catherwood, and Jacob Seidenberg relative to the study of the use of the injunction in labor disputes by courts in certain areas of New York state. The project included a quantitative study of the court records of New York and Kings Counties with the purpose of uncovering all the labor injunctions which were litigated from 1935 to June 1950. Also, the project included a study of the impact of the injunctions on collective bargaining relationships, which was accomplished by interviewing prominent lawyers involved in labor practice and by conducting some case studies of situations in which the injunction had been used. The study was included in the Senate Report, "State Court Injunctions," Senate Document Number 7, Eighty-First Congress, Second Session. Jacob Seidenberg conducted the study under Konvitz's supervision. Other material related to the Subcommittee's injunction study.
  - Injunction Study - Use of the Injunction (Joe Dye), 1951 (Box 17, Folder 3)